A Guide to the Papers of Fillmore Norfleet, 1931-1979
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Fillmore Norfleet, 1931-1979
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8809-h
This collection consists of 126 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift from Elizabeth Norfleet of Charlottesville, Virginia, to the Library on October 7, 1987.
Biographical/Historical Information
French teacher, biographer, genealogist.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Fillmore Norfleet (1903-1987), a French teacher at Woodberry Forest School, biographer, and genealogist, consist of typescripts of his translations of French novels, correspondence, and research material.
The novels translated by Norfleet include Jesus-the-Quail and Montmartre by Francis Carco, and The Other Sleep by Julien Green. Also present is a transcription of Jean Cocteau's Le Livre Blanc and Robert H. Fisher's Narrative of a Voyage to the West Indies(see # 3863).
Correspondents of the Norfleets include: Bernard Fay, Anne Green, Julien Green, Claude Swanson, the Marquis De Juigne, Yvonne Bezard, Francis Carco, Douglas Southall Freeman, and Jules Tramet.
Items of interest include: a Carter Glass autograph enclosed in a 1926 Claude Swanson letter; Anne Green writing about the effects of World War II upon her life (March 9, 1940); Julien Green concerning the translation of his novel The Other Sleep(March 29 & May 7, 1934; and May 26, 1944), and his University days (February 1 & July 6, 1960); and a letter from Francis Carco concerning his novel Jesus-the- Quail(May 3, 1934).
Norfleet's research material contains notes concerning the local history and genealogy of the Suffolk and Nansemond County, Virginia area; the Jamaica Ice Company Venture; and Dr. Robert Henning Fisher (1766-1815).
A miscellaneous folder contains newsclippings about Anne and Julien Green, Fillmore Norfleet, and "Midmont," home of Bernard Chamberlain; a copy of The University of Virginia Magazine May-June, 1934, with a "Reminiscence of Julian Green," by James Southall Wilson, and a reprinting of Green's first published short story, "The Apprentice Psychiatrist;" and two photographs, an undated photograph of Anne and Julien Green, and a view of Washington Square, Suffolk, Virginia (post 1888).
Contents List
- Jesus-the-Quail by Francis Carco, translated by Fillmore Norfleet 1937 Oct, (carbon).TMs (Box 1)
- Le Livre Blanc by Jean Cocteau n.d., Transcription.TMs (Box 1)
- Le Livre Blanc by Jean Cocteau n.d., carbon.Transcription. TMs (Box 1)
- Montmartre by Francis Carco, translated by Fillmore Norfleet 1937 Oct, TMs (Box 1)
- "Narrative of a Voyage to the West Indies" by Robert H. Fisher n.d., TMs (Box 1)
- The Other Sleep by Julien Green, translated by Fillmore Norfleet [post 1931], TMs, five copies, one a carbon, and one with pencilled (Box 1)
- Bernard Fay to Fillmore Norfleet 1934 Apr 10 & 14 (Box 2)
- Ann Green to Elizabeth Norfleet 1939-1940 (Box 2)
- Julien Green to Fillmore Norfleet 1934-1966,& n.d. (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1926-1979 (Box 2)
- Beppie(1881), by Mrs. E.T. Disosway n.d., electostatic copy (Box 2)
- Genealogical Research Notes, with some correspondence 1962-1973,& n.d. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Material ca. 1934-1971,& n.d. (Box 2)
- "Nansemond County Churches" in Colonial Churches of Tidewater Virginian.d., electrostatic copy (Box 2)
- Research material re the Jamaica Ice Company venture ca. 1953-1966,& n.d. (Box 2)
- Research Material re Dr. Robert Henning Fisher 1953, Correspondence of Fillmore Norfleet (Box 2)
- Sketch Book of Suffolk, Virginia. Its People and Its Trade, 1886 n.d., electrostatic copy (Box 2)
- Spanish exercise books 1938-1939 (Box 2)